<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue between riches, poverty, godliness, gravity, labour, and content: fit for the perusal of all that are sober-minded, in this time of unsetledness, and dis-satisfaction. By a friend to the publique.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E999_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207815</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866843</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119131</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119131)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E999[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue between riches, poverty, godliness, gravity, labour, and content: fit for the perusal of all that are sober-minded, in this time of unsetledness, and dis-satisfaction. By a friend to the publique.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Nehemiah Bradford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLIX. [1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Riches," .. "Content:" connected by brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. 21.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119131:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN
<list>
                  <item>Riches,</item>
                  <item>Poverty,</item>
                  <item>Godlineſs,</item>
                  <item>Gravity,</item>
                  <item>Labour, <hi>AND</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Content:</item>
               </list> Fit for the <hi>Peruſal</hi> of all that are <hi>Sober-minded,</hi> in this time of <hi>Unſetledneſs,</hi> and <hi>Diſ-Satisfaction. By a</hi> Friend <hi>to the Publique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nehemiah Bradford,</hi> MDCLIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="allegory">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119131:2"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE.</head>
            <p>THere dwelt once, as hath been ſaid, two Inhabitants in one Town, the one cal'd <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> the other <hi>Poverty.</hi> Theſe two could not long agree; for <hi>Riches</hi> would be inſulting over <hi>Poverty,</hi> either wronging and oppreſſing him, or ſcoffing at him, and abuſing him; and became ſo ſtately, that after a while he diſdained to look upon or ſpeak to him though his next neighbor. <hi>Poverty</hi> was as much to blame too, for he was as ſtout as <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> for the heart of him; and very foul mouthed, and could never afford <hi>Riches</hi> a good word behind his back, and grew full of envy and bitterneſs againſt him. Upon theſe continual jars, one of them muſt be gone. <hi>Riches</hi> would not ſtir, <hi>Poverty</hi> muſt, and gets him to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end of all the Town, and dwelt a while there, in a ſorry ruinous Cottage; which ſhortly after fell to the ground, and he was never able to repair it.</p>
            <p>There happened to come into thoſe parts a ſtranger nobly born, and of a far better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent then either of the former two; his name was <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> of a moſt ancient family; he is ſaid to have bin before the fall of <hi>Adam.</hi> His means were not great for his family was much decayed by many ſaid calamities they had undergone in ſome evil and troublous times; yet was he of ſo quiet, peaceable, and ſweet a diſpoſition, that he thought he could agree with any reaſonable neighbor in the world, if the fault were not his own. He came and took a houſe near <hi>Riches</hi> firſt; they long thus agreed, and had not ſo much as an unkind word paſſed between them, till <hi>Riches</hi> gave the firſt occaſion. <hi>Godlineſs</hi> was very induſtrious in his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, medled with no mans buſineſs but his own: Beſides, was very patient, pitiful, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; and, next to his conſtant care to pleaſe God, his deſire was to live without giving any juſt offence to any man living, for he would not wrong the leaſt child. But <hi>Riches</hi> grew every day more high and ſtately, as was not by <hi>Godlineſs</hi> to be endured; yet muſt he not be told of it neither. <hi>Godlineſs</hi> had born long: at length taking juſt offence at ſome of the ill wayes of <hi>Riches,</hi> told him mildly of it. But <hi>Riches</hi> ſaid he would not be control'd nor ſo affronted by the greateſt <hi>Godlineſs</hi> in the world: But brake out to him in the words the Sodemites u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Lot: This fellow came into ſojourn here a while ago, and he must needs become a Judge and a Lord:</hi> But I will not take it at thy hands.</p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>Riches</hi> had a many lewd and looſe ſervants, all bitter enemies to <hi>Godlineſs.</hi> Their names were <hi>Pride, Oppreſſion, Covetouſneſs, Luxury, Ryot, Prodigality, Malice, Flattery, Calumny,</hi> and <hi>Lazineſs;</hi> every one had his Office but <hi>Lazineſs,</hi> who ſaid he would wait on his Maſter at all turns, but he would undertake no other imployment. <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> was his chief ſervant, &amp; ſteward of his houſe, a cruel enemy to the Poor. <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> was his <hi>Bayliff, Pride</hi> was his <hi>Taylor,</hi> yet no good workman neither; for let him take his meaſure how he would, and make his garment with all the skill he had, the making, or the ſtuff, or the colour, or the faſhion, or the trimming, or the putting on, did not pleaſe, at leaſt if they did one day, did not two days together, neither him nor his wife (her name was <hi>Jezabel,</hi> ſo was her mother's befere her, who learnt her to paint and to patch; and to powder; and her Waiting-woman Miſtris <hi>Lightskirt Curioſity.) Prodigality</hi> was upper Butler, and under him <hi>Ryot;</hi> and the <hi>cup</hi> they all drank in was called <hi>Exceſs,</hi> a foul great cup it was: &amp; looking on it, to ſee what mark it had, I obſerved 3 letters, but all 3 D's; but yet not ſtanding together, but the one near <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> brim, the 2d in the middle, the 3d in the bottom. Many would gheſs what theſe 3 letters might mean ſome ſaid it was <hi>Donum Domini Divitiarum</hi> the name of the <hi>Donour.</hi> But they of the houſe ſaid the firſt D. was <hi>Delight,</hi> the 2d <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> and the 3d was <hi>Drowzineſs.</hi> But there dwelt an old man not far off, whoſe name was <hi>Gravity,</hi> a comely old man, of much lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and great experience; upon whoſe counſel all the Neighbors did much rely; yea, I have known when <hi>Labor</hi> &amp; <hi>Godlineſs</hi> &amp; <hi>Content</hi> too, have gone to adviſe with him; but he had bin diſcharg'd from looking into <hi>Riches</hi> his houſe, he told me theſe 3 letters were ſet on by the ſame hand that wrote the 3 words on <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> wall, and that the firſt D. did ſignifie <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe,</hi> the 2d D. <hi>Death,</hi> and the 3d he was ſure was <hi>Damnation.</hi> And were it not too long a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119131:2"/> I could tell you what children <hi>Riches</hi> had, and what Grand-children; and ſince I hear what is become of all. <hi>Riches</hi> was now an old man; he had 2 Sons and 2 Daughters. Both his Sons died without iſſue in their Fathers life, ſo that he ſaw his name was like to periſh, what ever became of the eſtate. The elder ſon was called <hi>Honor,</hi> the Fathers darling, and the hopes of all the family; but a weak child he was, and never like to be long lived: he died young, and put all the houſe into mourning, they lament the loſs of <hi>Honor</hi> to this day. The yonger ſon was call'd <hi>Ambition,</hi> one of an haughty &amp; aſpiring mind, and of a working reſtleſs ſpirit; he was one ſtill in every deſperate and miſchievous plot; was betraid, &amp; came to an untimely and ſhameful end, and no man pitied him. The 2 Daughters were <hi>Delicacy</hi> the elder (more like the mother) and <hi>Avarice</hi> the yonger (more like the father.) The elder was always an unruly and wanton Girl, never like to come to good; and when her mother had provided a great match for her preferment, ſhe had caſt her ſelf away upon one of her fathers Serving men call'd <hi>Prodigality</hi> (they agreed like dogs and cats) and they had an only daughter whoſe name was <hi>Infamy. Avarice</hi> was reſolved to be ruled by her father; &amp; by his perſwaſion, ſhe was beſtow'd on his Steward <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> his chief ſervant, whom he ſaid he loved as dearly as if he had bin his own child: he told his daughter <hi>Avarice</hi> he would make the beſt husband for her in the world; that they were ſure never to want, they nor theirs, for if ſhe could but ſave, the husband would be ſure to get. But they had not a good day toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neither, but lived quite beſides what they had; &amp; they had an onely daughter, whoſe name was <hi>Miſery.</hi> Theſe 2 Grandchildren, <hi>Infamy</hi> &amp; <hi>Miſery,</hi> is all that at preſent are left of <hi>Riches</hi> race they are yet living, and like to live many a day. But to return to his ſervants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: <hi>Luxury</hi> was his Cook <hi>Gluttony</hi> his Carver, <hi>Malice</hi> was his Secretary: But he made moſt of two above all the reſt: <hi>Flattery</hi> the one, his greateſt Favourite; and <hi>Calumny</hi> the other: theſe 2 had the length of his foot; the one could make him angry, &amp; the other pleaſed with whom they would, &amp; whenſoever they liſted. I had like to have forgot his <hi>Chaplain;</hi> for he would be thought to be religious too; his name was Sir <hi>John Reader.</hi> He was no Scholar at all, though he ſaid he had taken a degree in the Univerſity. But he had 2 properties which gave general content to all the houſe: he could mumble them over a few ſhort prayers out of the Book, and when he had done, he could bowl &amp; drink, and ſwear with the beſt of 'em, all the day after. Now the houſe being ſtored with ſuch ſervants, there was nothing but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order to be ſeen: they could none of them endure <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> but made ſongs of him, ſcoffed &amp; jeered at him and all his <hi>actions;</hi> yea, made themſelves merry with his very <hi>geſtures,</hi> and quarrel'd with his children &amp; ſervants. Nor did they well agree among themſelves, for <hi>Prodigality</hi> &amp; <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> could never agree, though <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> held toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Malice, Calumny</hi> &amp; <hi>Flattery</hi> often jarred &amp; differed. And as for <hi>Ryot,</hi> he could agree with never a one, but onely <hi>Pride. Godlineſs</hi> comes to <hi>Riches</hi> in a courteous way, &amp; tells him privately of their miſcarriages; &amp; withall tels him, if he keep theſe ſervants longer, they will undo him for ever; perſwades him to reform his family &amp; to turn away theſe old ſervants, &amp; he would commend better to him, which ſhould be more for his credit &amp; profit too. But <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> grew very hot, &amp; would not hear him ſpeak; but fell foul on <hi>Godlineſs</hi> calling his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to help him: and firſt of all, his <hi>Chaplain,</hi> who was no ways able to hold argument with <hi>Godlineſs;</hi> but he could out-rail <hi>Godlineſs</hi> &amp; <hi>Gravity</hi> both: he would needs bring Scripture to confute <hi>Godlineſs;</hi> and he had one place very ready, being all he was acquainted with <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Be not righteous over-much, neither make thy ſelf over-wiſe: for why ſhouldſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf?</hi> Here he had thought he had knocked <hi>Godlineſs</hi> down. But <hi>Godlineſs</hi> had his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ready, &amp; bad him read the next words: <hi>Be not over-much wicked, neither be thou foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l ſh: why ſhouldſt thou die before the time?</hi> Sir <hi>John</hi> was preſently nonpluſt, that he had not a word of Scripture more, but fell to downright railing. Then did <hi>Riches</hi> call for his other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to ſecond his <hi>Chaplain,</hi> and bade <hi>Pride, Malice</hi> &amp; <hi>Calumny</hi> pay him ſoundly, &amp; if they 4 were not able to do it, he would ſend for <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> to ſet him further off; for next his old mortal enemy <hi>Poverty,</hi> whom he had ſent packing, he proteſted to hate <hi>Godlineſs</hi> more then any creature alive; yea, he ſwore to it too, that he hated him more then he did the very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. And old <hi>Jezabel</hi> looking out of her Window, cry'd, ſpare him not, knock him down, or ſend him packing; for I cannot abide the very looks of him.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119131:3"/>
            <p>Now Godlineſſe had a few Servants of his own training up, well bred, fit to ſerve the beſt Noble-man in the Land; but he had not many to ſpare: he had tryed to breed up more, but he could do no good on many of them, or they would not tarry with him. Such a one was <hi>Ignorance,</hi> but he reſolved not to be taught, and he ſaid he never came thither to be <hi>Catechized. Error</hi> would have dwelt with <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> too, as he ſaid; but he muſt have the Liberty of his Conſcience, as he cal'd it. <hi>Singularity</hi> made offer of his Service; but he would indent with him to go hear when and where he pleaſed. <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> was more importunate then any one, to be his chief Servant, and companion too; and with his fair language and Scripture-expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, he had wrought himſelf for a while into a fair Opinion with <hi>Godlineſſe;</hi> Oh! he had ſuch a Tongue, that he was able to deceive any man alive: and indeed he began ſo well, that had his deed been as good as his word, and had he held out as he began, he had been an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary good ſervant: yea, <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> would fain have been exerciſing his gifts; and ſaid he had ſpoken often in private meetings, with great applauſe; but he never cared for joyning in prayer with others; and they could never perceive that he uſed any private prayer by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; therefore his Maſter fell into ſuſpition of him, firſt for his much talk, and his many brags; and having ſet two of his old tryed ſervants to obſerve him, <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Sincerity,</hi> they inform'd their Maſter, they found him out to be a very cheat, a notorious lyer, and ſuch a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning diſſembler, that ye could not tell when to believe him; yea, they ſet him out to be ſuch a dangerous fellow, that he was enough to ſpoil the whole Family, at leaſt to bring up an ill report againſt them all; therefore they deſired their Maſter to rid the houſe ſpeedily of him, or there was no ſtaying for them. <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> preſently calls for him, and admoniſheth him to mend his manners, and in a great paſſion (for it was ſaid, he was never ſo much moved with any one in all his life) he charged him to be preſently put out of doors, and never to come near his houſe, unleſſe he brought <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> along to paſſe their word for him, that he was now another man; Nay, <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> was ſo paſſionate, that for his ſake he ſaid he would never have any one of that name come into his family again.</p>
            <p>And would you think it? <hi>Idleneſſe</hi> had a mind to the Service: but he asked great wages, and yet would do nothing; nor would he ſo much as promiſe to mend. But he had a few faithfull Servants, whoſe names were <hi>Faith, Hope, Charity, Repentance, Experience, Humility, Sincerity, Temperance, Sobriety,</hi> &amp;c. He had alſo many good friends; all the old <hi>Patriarks,</hi> and holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> were his near kinſmen, and intimate acquaintance; and he is ſaid to derive his pedigree from the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> from whom he is lineally deſcended; and his Wives name was <hi>Philadelphia.</hi> But his Servants he keeps all hard to work, and among them is not the leaſt difference or diſcord in the World; but they lived in the greateſt peace and quietneſſe that could be; till <hi>Riches</hi> ſervants, and thoſe meeting, there would be old falling out preſently; for the diſordered company that <hi>Riches</hi> kept, would be ſtill offering ſome abuſe or other to them; and upon complaint made to their Maſter, he ſaid he would maintain them in it, and had ſet them on of purpoſe to weary out <hi>Godlineſſe;</hi> and that he was at the charge of a <hi>Chaplain</hi> onely to oppoſe the <hi>Power of Godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> thus driven away by <hi>Riches</hi> means, and his ſervant <hi>Oppreſſion;</hi> removes to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry end of all the Town, where <hi>Poverty</hi> dwelt, in an old ruinous ſhed, without either door or Window, or ſire, or Chimney, or ſo much as a bed to lye upon; yet extream ſtout, often boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of his Family, and what his Anceſtors had been, as good as <hi>Riches;</hi> and I think no leſſe; for whereas <hi>Riches</hi> could pretend to no higher pedigree then <hi>Nabal,</hi> of whom he was begotten when he lay ſick of the <hi>Stone in his Heart,</hi> and died a few dayes after, whence all the Poſterity have had that diſeaſe hereditarily cleaving to them more or leſſe; <hi>Poverty</hi> would vaunt often that he could derive his Pedigree from <hi>Noah;</hi> for <hi>Cham</hi> his Son was his Great Grandfather; and his Motto he keeps to this day, <hi>A ſervant of ſervants.</hi> But I rather think he may carry his Pedigree beyond <hi>Noah,</hi> and ſpring from the loins of <hi>Cain;</hi> who after he was driven from the preſence of the Lord, had this Legacy given him, that he and all his poſterity ſhould be <hi>Vagabonds</hi> and <hi>Runnagates. Godlineſſe</hi> expecting more quietneſſe, intending not to wrong <hi>Poverty</hi> of one farthing, but to do him all the good he could; <hi>Poverty</hi> was ſtout and ſcornfull, and his Wife a naſty <hi>Slut,</hi> poor children they had, all in rags. He had never a Servant, nor had he had many a day. This <hi>Poverty</hi> was an ill Husband; if he got a penny, he muſt to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119131:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Godlineſs</hi> being thus unkindly dealt with, &amp; driven out of Town both by <hi>Riches</hi> &amp; <hi>Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> was a while much perplexed whither he ſhould remove to find a reſting place, and where to meet <hi>Content</hi> his beſt friend on earth, which was his firſt Deſign. He was once wiſhed by a Friend, that had obſerved his lovely aſpect and his ſweet behaviour, to go to the <hi>Court,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all men go to ſeek preferment; and if any did riſe, it were pity but ſuch a one as he ſhould be promoteed: How much good might he do his friends and himſelf, if he were in place? But <hi>Godlineſs</hi> replied, he had bin bred up in a plain and private way; he had not much means, nor many friends; without which what is to be expected at Court? nor could he skill of the Court-Language and Complements, neither was he at all acquainted with theſe Arts of <hi>Simulation</hi> and <hi>Diſſimulation,</hi> which are ſaid to be all in all in a perfect Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier: Therefore he reſolved all the preferments in the world ſhould not entice him to do any thing againſt his Conſcience. Next he was by ſome friends wiſht to go and liſt himſelf in the Army: he anſwered, Of all lives he liked that leaſt, yet for his part, he ſaid, beſides the hazard ſuch run in the Wars, he was not well ſatisfied in the juſtice of the Cauſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the one ſide or other. And he judged the Souldiers Calling to be onely warrantable when the Cauſe was plain and clear, and ſo long as <hi>Neceſſity</hi> puts them into Arms, and no longer. He profeſſed, for his part, he loved the Souldiers ſo well, that he did wiſh with all his heart, that all the Souldiers would turn Godly; but he loved <hi>Godlineſs</hi> ſo well, that he could not wiſh all Godly men to turn Souldiers. Then he was by ſome perſwaded to go abroad into the World and travel, then might he obſerve the divers manners and faſhions of other Countries, &amp; grow acquainted with their ſeveral Religions and Languages: That he was not a Gentleman who had not travelled, nor was any a complete man without this. He preſently replyed, he had been a Traveller already a long time, toward Heaven, and his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey was as near or nearer a way thither then any other. His deſign was to grow in Grace, &amp; that he feared was not to be promoted by going into forraign Parts: and for their Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, let others affect them; if he could learn the old Language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> it was enough for him; and though he would judge no man, he had obſerved few returned better by Travels, as to their Religion: yea, he remembred of the 12 choſen men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that were ſent out to view other Countries, there were but two who returned the ſame men they went out; the reſt had caſt oft God, were corrupt in their Principles, and did much miſchief to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men. He was once ſet upon by a Fryer, who tempted him to go into a Cloyſter, and to induce him thereunto, he was urgent for him to go ſee their Chappel how it was adorned, and to hear their Muſick: and fain would have perſwaded him to believe, if any where in the World, there was to be ſeen <hi>Devotion</hi> &amp; <hi>Sanstity.</hi> He preſently replyed with indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Away with your Devotion and Sanctity: Sanctity ſo utterly oppoſite to Sincerity, and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on totally deſtructive to the power of Godlineſs.</hi> At laſt, he ſequeſter'd himſelf in ſome nook, in a ſolitary manner, out of all commerce with others. There might he hope quietly to retire himſelf be free from Perſecutions, which he ſaw did every where attend him; there might he be out of the ſight of open Prophaneſs (more grievous to a godly mind then Perſecution it ſelf) there might he enjoy God, the liberty of his Conſcience, and pour out his Soul in inceſſant Prayers, and enjoy communion with his Soul-beloved Saviour. This was mighty pleaſing: But he remembred that man was made for Society; and he had thoſe Scriptures came to his mind: <hi>None of us live to our ſelves, We are members one of another, None of us are to ſeek our own things onely, but every one for the good of others.</hi> And he called to mind how prejudicial <hi>Solitude</hi> had ever been to the beſt of men. That God had ſaid, it was not good for the <hi>firſt-Adam,</hi> no not in <hi>innocency,</hi> to be alone; nor was it ſafe for the <hi>firſt-woman</hi> to be alone, even in <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> nor was it ſafe for the <hi>ſecond-Adam,</hi> the firſt begotten of the whole Creation, and the onely Conquerer of the Divel, to be alone in a <hi>Wilderneſs:</hi> He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded therefore, That it was exceſs of Paſſion and Zeal, which tranſported <hi>David</hi> &amp; <hi>Jeremy,</hi> to wiſh themſelves into a Wilderneſs; and doubtleſs that it was unavoidable Perſecutions which drove <hi>Elias</hi> and others, into their Caves and Solitudes: for his part, he thought he was bound to honour God, as much as was poſſible, by doing good to Humane Society.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119131:4"/>
            <p>After ſometime ſpent in this unſetled condition, it pleaſed God to bring Godlineſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>father Gravity,</hi> of whom I made mention before; a true friend and faithful. Counſellor, to all who adviſed with him. A comely old man, and of much experience: he knew both Court and Countrey; and there was ſcarcely any paſſage of note in his time, or long before, but he was well acquainted with it.</p>
            <p>Godlineſs was much cheared, when he ſaw his amiable and lovely countenance, and his long gray hairs; Diſcourſeth much with him, and receives the beſt ſatisfaction from him, that he had met with many a day: after much good and ſerious conference, he enquireth of him, it he could inform him where a convenient Houſe might be had for money, Town or Countrey. He tells, he was glad he asked, that he might both help a Neighbor to ſo good a Tenant; and him (though a ſtranger as yet) to ſo good accommodations. He bids him return to the Town again, and about the middle of it, turn aſide a little out of the Road; there dwelt juſt mid-way, as he could gueſs, between Riches and Poverty, old La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, a good honeſt Neighbour, and the beſt Houſe keeper in all the Pariſh; He had a convenient Houſe to let, and would be glad of a good Tenant: for he was loath any thing ſhould lie dead upon his hand.</p>
            <p>Thither then he goes, as he was directed; and when he came to knock at his door, he found him within; he was ſeldom abroad; and he had been hard at work, with his Wife <hi>Prudence</hi> (a comely Woman, and a very cleanly Houſwife) ſitting cloſe to her Wheel; and the Children all of them doing ſomewhat. They were all in a handſom habit of good Broad-cloth; no Lace or Trimming that was coſtly, but whole and handſom. The houſe without well built, and in good repair; within very near, every room well furniſht. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, Labors pedigree was very ancient; he came of <hi>Adam's</hi> ſecond Sonne, innocent <hi>Abel,</hi> who learnt him firſt to keep ſheep, then to ſpin the wooll; and Labour was all the iſſue he left behinde him, when he died. This Labour ſaid moreover, That his Anceſtors had done the greateſt exploits that the World had ever ſeen: That they had built all thoſe great and ancient Cities in the World, all Towns, Forts, Caſtles, and Bridges: That <hi>Ninive, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, Rome, Conſtantinople, Jeruſalem,</hi> were all built by Labors own hands: That Labor had fought many a ſore Battel, gained many famous Victories, conquered moſt Nations, gained the greateſt Dominions, ſtabliſhed the wholſomeſt Lawes and Rules of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; had traveled all Countries, had been at tho <hi>Indies,</hi> and thence brought and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported all their richeſt Pearls, Spices and Commodities, and traffiqued with them into all other Countries: That the <hi>Pyramides</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and all the other Wonders of the World, were of Labours own handy-work and foundation: That he had invented Tillage, improved Lands, levelled Mountains, drained Fens, invented all Arts and Sciences; bred the beſt Scholars; and the moſt excellent Books extant, were of his compoſing. Godlineſs tells him, he had heard much good of him, and that his Anceſtors, and Labor's, were old acquaintance, and had loved dearly, living neighborly together; and therefore he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to take that Houſe he had to let, and that he would be as good a Tenant as he could let it to; and promiſed h m, he ſhould loſe nothing by him. He told him moreover, it was Godlineſs which learnt Labor the firſt way of thriving; and that it was their two Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers together, who had performed the moſt renowned undertakings. Labor indeed had done very much, but by Godlineſs's directions and expence. The moſt pious and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Acts, witneſs <hi>Noahs-Ark,</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, The one built by Labor hands, but at the ſole charge and by the Divine direction of Godlineſs; and the other, though every ſtone and piece of Timber was hewed and made ready, and joyned together by Labors pains; yet it was Godlineſs's purſe that payd for all, and maintained the ſervice, and found the daily ſacrifice: It was Labor indeed that fetcht the ſtone and timber from <hi>Lebanon;</hi> but it was onely Godlineſs, without Labor, that fetcht the fire from Heaven. And if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth was upheld by Labor, it was onely Godlineſs the Church was raiſed, ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and preſerved by. It was Godlineſs that ſpread the Goſpel, converted Infidels, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually aſſiſted all the famous Prophets and Apoſtles; and doth to this day enable the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters in the happy employment and ſucceſs in their Miniſtery. And if Labor had at any time put forth any uſeful Writings, yet the beſt Books which were in the World, were all of Godlineſs's putting forth.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119131:4"/>
            <p>They were ſoon agreed, and agreed moſt lovingly together, and reſolved never to part. <hi>Labors</hi> Houſe ſtood in a very wholſom air, near the Church; vvhich made <hi>Godlineſs</hi> like it the better: the whole Houſe very healthful; ſeldom was any ſick there, not did they die till full of dayes. The Children looked all with ruddy and live y countenances: you might know whoſe Children they were, by their very faces. A few ſervants there were, called <hi>Forecaſt, Diligence, Expedition, Chearfulneſs, Perſeverance;</hi> good riſers all, and tough work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: But Labour ſet many poor people a work, and payd them duly; and by that means inabled many, poor before, to pay their debts, and to provide comfortably for themſelves and their Families, and to relieve the poor; yea, Labor provided Stocks and Penſions for their Widows and Children of ſuch, who had been honeſt and careful in their buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Labour had lived well before; but when Goodneſs became his Neighbour, you would wonder how he came on and increaſed, as if <hi>Jacob</hi> had been come again into <hi>Laban's</hi> fields, or <hi>Joſeph</hi> into <hi>Potiphers</hi> houſe, or the Ark into <hi>Obed-Edom.</hi> For Godlineſs taught him how to ſeek, and get a bleſſing for him and his; brought him to pray in his Family, to inſtruct his children and ſervants in Catechizing, to call upon God, as duly as to riſe out of their beds; and to fly-lying, ſwearing, profaneneſs, and irreligiouſneſs, as much as idleneſs. And he told him withall, there was a friend of his was ſhortly to come that way (for he had a good promiſe for it) who would make them both happy: his name was <hi>Content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould have told you alſo, That though there vvas an old Church hard by Labor's houſe, when Godlineſs came thither, yet it was much gone to decay; and, which was more trouble to Godlineſs, there was no Miniſter: there had been one it ſeemes ſome years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (a Godly ancient man, and very painful:) Labor told him, he preached, Catechized, and expounded conſtantly; he did not think there vvas a Pariſh in a good vvay, better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: It vvould have done you good, to ſee how people loved the Church, kept the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and vvhat love vvas among the Neighbors. But that good old man vvas dead, and now No-body cared vvhether they had a Miniſter or no: They thought any body that could ſpeak, might preach; and as for Prayer, and reading the Scripture, ſinging of Pſalms, and the Sacraments, he ſaw there vvere few did regard them now a dayes; and if the Church ſhould fall down to the ground, he knew none vvould take care to repair it. There vvere many ſufficient men in the Pariſh, he ſaid; but they loved their money too vvell: and there vvas one above all the reſt, called Riches, vvorth thouſands; but he vvas nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friend to the poor, nor the Church; but vvould rather ſpend 100 l. on his Pride, Luxury, and Ryot, then allow 40 s. towards the maintenance of a good Miniſter. But as for me, ſaid Labor, as poor a man as I am, if my Neighbors vvould be ruled by me, vve vvould not for ſhame let the Church fall, and live like Heathens, vvithout one to guid us: whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever vvill be at the coſt, I vvould beſtow my pains; and it ſhould go hard, but I vvould find ſomewhat for ſuch a good vvork. Gods bleſſing on thy heart, ſaid Godlineſs; I ſhall love thee the better for it, vvhile I know thee: vve will between us, ſee to get the Church fitted, and then look out for a Miniſter; and if thou vvilt be at the pains, I will bear all the charges, vvhatſoever it coſt, though I leave the leſſe to my Children.</p>
            <p>My Anceſtors have alwayes been great friends to the Church and a godly Miniſtery; They have at heir own charge, built many Churches from the ground, and richly endowed them for the comfortable maintaining of the Miniſter, vvhen they had done. One of my Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors, called <hi>Obadiah,</hi> had alone p ovided an hundred Prophets in a time of a famine, fed them with bread and vvater by fifty in a Cave, vvhich vvas as good fare as he had him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and he believed, none of his friends vvere ever the poorer for ſuch good vvorks; but ſtill God had bleſſed them the more abundantly. He for his part vvere not vvorthy to be called by the name of Godlineſs, if he ſhould be backward in ſuch a buſineſs: and his Wife <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> he vvas ſure, vvould put her helping hand; for ſhe vvas once Siſter to <hi>Dorcas,</hi> that vvas ſo full of good vvorks, and alms deeds vvhich ſhe did, and vvas ſo much lamented, vvhen ſhe vvas dead and gone. To be ſhort, they concluded between them to fall upon the vvork; and the Church was but newly repaired in a plain and decent manner, and a good Miniſter ſetled in the place, vvhen <hi>Content</hi> came.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Content</hi> is not of earthly extraction, never came out of the loins of <hi>Adam</hi> at all; But I ſuppoſe might be that <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> who had neither Father or Mother recorded on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119131:5"/> earth: and ſure I am, it was <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> which bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Poſterity. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain I am, he was with <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, before his fall; and before his Creation, among the Angels; and before their Creation, had been with the bleſſed Trinity from all eternity. He was not often ſeen on earth, ſince <hi>Adams</hi> exile out of Paradiſe; yet now and then hath he given a vi t to ſome of Labours friends, and Godlineſs acquaintance.</p>
            <p>He is alway attended with many gallant followers: his chief friends, I well remember, of whom he made moſt account, were called <hi>Juſtification, Adoption, Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance;</hi> and one above all the reſt, called <hi>Peace of Conſcience.</hi> He was wont alſo often to ſpeak of a great Benefactor, long ſince deceaſed, to whom he was infinitely obliged, who had been the maker of him: he would ſay, how dearly he had loved him; he ſtill called him his Lord and Saviour at every word (ſure then it could be no other, then the Son of God) how he had done and ſuffered much for his ſake, who had never deſerved the leaſt favour from him; that had it not been for his ſingular bounty, and extreme ſufferings, his name had never been Content; but ſin, miſery, and deſpair; for he had been in great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and danger, having many great enemies to deal with, and many unconceiveable ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities lay upon him, But by flying to him, acquaintance with him, and ſubmiſſion to his yoke, he had found this unexpreſſible reſt to his Soul. He related alſo, how he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on him a Coat of divers colours; one ſo pure white, as no <hi>Fuller</hi> on Earth could whiten; which is the clear Linnen and white, the righteouſneſs of Saints, called the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Sanctification: The other ſo red, as the pureſt blood on Earth, not the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> could make ſo pure red.</p>
            <p>This is the righteouſneſs of believers, known by the name of the righteouſneſs of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication before the Throne of God. And that he had, beſides much grace already beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, promiſed him a rich Robe, and Crown of Glory.</p>
            <p>He and his retinue, make that place and family happy, whereſoever they do but lodge. This noble <hi>Content,</hi> in his return homewards, cal'd in at <hi>Poverty's</hi> ſhed, enquiring if there were any room for ſuch gueſts; they ſaid no, but likely at the end of the Town, where <hi>Riches</hi> dwelt, there they might find entertainment. Thither they went, and deſired entrance, but were anſwered, That none neither knew him or any of his company, nor ever heard of ſuch names, unleſſe at a houſe <hi>Midway</hi> between this and <hi>Poverties,</hi> cal'd <hi>Godlineſſes,</hi> next door to <hi>Labors.</hi> There they had heard of ſome ſuch unuſual and out-landiſh names, as <hi>Sobriety, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,</hi> &amp;c. ſo ſhut the door upon him. Thither this noble man comes, and knocks: <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> opens the door, and knew him ſo ſoon as he ſee him. He told him he had long expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and had room enough for him and his company. <hi>Content</hi> ſaid, A little room is enough for thee and me, We have not long to ſtay here, away we muſt, and at our fathers houſe is that will make amends for all. Now did <hi>Labor</hi> think himſelf happy, that ever <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> came to be his neighbor, and teach him his <hi>Mystery;</hi> and a better Art, the way of thriving, <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> himſelf was much happier alſo, <hi>Content</hi> dwelling with him, who joyned with him in prayer and other duties. Reader, I thou wouldſt know Contentments Lodgings, it is in an inner room of <hi>Godlineſſes,</hi> cal'd <hi>Sincerity,</hi> hung round with <hi>Purity of heart,</hi> the next door to <hi>Labors;</hi> there I deſire thee to reſt, promiſing to come to thee, where (I am ſure) we ſhall be happy: for what can make a man ſo happy on earth, as <hi>Godlineſſe with Content, which</hi> is <hi>the greateſt gain; having not onely the promiſes of the life which now is, but of that which is to come;</hi> through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, who is the Crown of Crowns to <hi>Content,</hi> as <hi>Content</hi> is the Crown of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> the Crown of <hi>Labor,</hi> where there ſhall be no</p>
            <trailer>END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
